Welcome to Mariners Online. So glad that you're joining us because we're going to look at what I think is one of the most important passages in all of the Bible. Are you allowed to say that? Can there be one passage that's more important than the others?
Because they're all words from God and they're inspired, and I guess you probably can't say that it's the most important. So, you know, maybe you could say it's like in the top three. But if you say even top three, well then you're measuring it against, and it's all inspired, and I'm not sure I can say the top three. But I could say it's one of my favorites. But then again, it seems like every time I teach, I'm saying this is my favorite passage.
So let me just tell you why I think that this is one of the most important passages in all of the Bible, and then you can decide. Today, we're going to look at a passage that gives us the most complete picture of who Jesus is. It tells us who Jesus is, what he did, and then the implications for our life. So I want you to look at that. So read with me, and then you can decide what's the most important thing about this passage.
Look at what it says in Philippians 2. You must have the same attitude that Christ Jesus had. Though he was God, he did not think equality with God was something to cling to. Instead, he gave up his divine privileges. He took the humble position of a slave and was born as a human being.
When he appeared in human form, he humbled himself in obedience to God and died a criminal's death on a cross. Therefore, God elevated him to the place of highest honor and gave him the name above all other names, that at the name of Jesus every knee should bow, in heaven and on earth and under the earth, and every tongue declare that Jesus Christ is Lord, to the glory of God the Father. This is why I love this passage, because what it does is it gives us this complete picture of who Jesus is. First of all, what's the first thing it tells us about Jesus?
Clearly, he says in this passage, Jesus is God. Look at what it says. You must have the same attitude that Christ Jesus had, though he was God.
So he's clearly saying it. Jesus' identity is God. Jesus' character is God. His essence is God. And this is the defining issue of Christianity, and it is the dividing issue, which is the identity of Jesus. People are fine if you say that Jesus was a good teacher, a prophet, or a wonderful man, but they want to get out from under the weight of the idea that Jesus is God.
Because if Jesus is God, it has huge implications. So ever since Jesus came, people have tried to deny that he's God, and they do it in two ways. They say Jesus never claimed to be God, and Jesus' followers didn't believe that he was God. And neither one of those is true. And I want to show you. You can see it really easily.
Jesus clearly claimed to be God. In John chapter 10, Jesus was speaking, and the religious leaders understood what he said, and because he claimed to be God, they pick up stones and they're going to kill him, which was a first-century way of killing a heretic. And Jesus actually said, Why are you going to stone me? And the people said, the religious leaders, You, as a man, claim to be God.
So it's very clear they heard Jesus claim to be God. In Mark chapter 2, Jesus is teaching, and four friends bring their paralyzed friend to Jesus. They tear up a roof and they lower him down in front of Jesus. Jesus looks at him, and he looks at the religious leaders, and he says, Your sins are forgiven.
And the religious leaders lose their mind because they're saying that you can't say that. Only God can forgive sins. And so Jesus looks at them and says, So which is easier to say, stand up and walk, or your sins are forgiven? And they don't want any part of the quiz because they don't want to be trapped.
And it's obviously way easier to say your sins are forgiven than to stand up, you know, and be healed. And Jesus says, so that you know that I am God, I'm going to heal him. And he turns to the man and he says, stand up and walk, and the man does it. So Jesus clearly, over and again, there is no doubt Jesus claims to be God. The second one, people say, well, Jesus followers never really believed that he was God.
And their argument goes like this, that they said that what Jesus said was exaggerated and embellished over time and over hundreds of years. People that are followers of Jesus came to believe that he claimed to be God or that he was God, but the initial followers didn't believe that. But that's not true. And it is this passage that is the passage that shows us that this is not true.
This passage that we just read out of Philippians 2 was written 25 years after the crucifixion and the resurrection. And what is being quoted here by Paul is a creed or confession of the early church. That means within 10, 15 years of the crucifixion and the resurrection, people were declaring that were eyewitnesses of Jesus, people who saw Jesus teach, people who saw Jesus do miracles, saw the crucifixion, saw the resurrection.
They claimed that Jesus was God. And the reason, again, if you get lost, this is why it's so important. The most important Christians believe, the most important issue in life is the identity of Jesus. John Stott, in his book Basic Christianity, says this: The claims of Jesus and his followers are so extreme, it is impossible to have a moderate response.
People hated Jesus and wanted to kill him. They feared him and they just wanted to run from him. Because he claimed to be God, or they were overwhelmed by him and they surrendered their life to him and followed him. But no one just liked Jesus as a good teacher. He was either delusional or crazy, or that he was who he said to be.
And this passage is the defining passage where Jesus says that he is God, or that Jesus claims to be God, and this changes everything. It changes who we are and the way that we think, because what we understand is we have a Savior to our rescue who is God. God didn't send someone else. He didn't send an emissary. He himself came to save us and to rescue us.
And this is wonderful news. Paul celebrates this in Romans chapter 8, where he says that if God is for us, who can be against us? There's no condemnation. No one can condemn us because it's Jesus who declares that we are righteous because he is God. Nothing can separate us from God's love, not trouble or calamity or persecution, danger or death, and we have no reason to fear.
So we have unquenchable optimism because God is for us. He loves us. He provides for us. He works on our behalf. He's a God who is always standing with us. And so we don't, you know, even though we live in a world of heartbreak and pain and sadness, and that's just a part of life, we don't live a pessimistic or a down or a hopeless or a negative life. We live a life with unquenchable joy. Does that make sense?
Let me give you an illustration of it. My wife turned 70 just this past week. I know, 70. She's really old. And so she wanted a gift, and I gave her a ring, but this is an Oura ring. And you've seen lots of people have them. They're a technology ring, and this ring tells you a number of things about your health.
But specifically, it tells you how you slept, you know, how long it took you to go to sleep, how deep your sleep was, your REMs, you know, and the whole thing just gives you a whole breakdown of your sleep patterns. And so just the other day, two days ago, Gloria comes, and she joins me for coffee. We always start the morning to coffee together around a table, and we talk about what we're going to do for the day. And she comes in, and she comes in, and she is dragging. And I said, Did you not sleep well? And she goes, No, I didn't have a good night's sleep.
I was sleepless. I tossed and turned. I feel like I woke up. I am tired. I am dragging. And I said, What does your ring say?
You know, your Oura ring. She goes, Oh, that's a good idea. So she pulls it out, and she starts looking at her phone, and she goes, Wow, I went to bed pretty quick last night. And you know what? I got a good amount of deep sleep, it says. And I had good times of REM sleep. And he goes, You know what this says?
That I had a good night's sleep. And as she's explaining it to me, you can see this tired person all of a sudden start to sit up more straight. Her countenance has got this excitement and energy to life. And she goes, This is going to be a good day. I'm ready to go. That's what this truth is. These truths that Jesus is God, that he loves us, that he's for us, that he's with us, that, you know, that nothing can stand against us, is this Oura ring truth that brings joy and optimism to our life and gives us a sense of resilience, spiritual resilience, that we can do whatever we need to do today as we face the day.
We don't live in fear. We don't live defeated. We don't live overwhelmed. Well, God is for us. He's with us. Jesus is God.
That's the first thing. And then the second thing that is a profound implication, I learned in my late twenties, I read something that Saint Augustine wrote about this, and I really liked it because when you say Jesus is God, immediately you're faced with the idea of the Trinity, that there's God the Father, there's God the Son, and the God the Spirit, and that there's three gods, and if you have any one of them, you have all God. God the Father is all God. Jesus is all God. The Spirit is all God. And so how can there, you know, be one? And I can't explain the Trinity to you, but I love the implication he drew from this because he said this.
He said, People who believe in only one God... Have a defective, imperfect, and incomplete view of God, or an incomplete God. Because if there's only one God, that God never knew love or understood love until he created angels and people. And basically, if he created angels and people because he needed love, he was trying—he created people to use them.
And that is not the God of the Bible and the God of the Trinity. What the Bible teaches us is that God lived in loving relationship with himself, in the sense that there was God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Spirit, and they lived in communal family love together. And then the reason they create is that they are inviting us into that relationship of love, not to extract something from us, but to give something to us.
And I really like that. I really like that idea, and it has huge implications for us because, so when we love or serve or give to someone, and we do it to meet our needs, to extract something from a person, to somehow get something from them, we are not loving as this passage says in the same attitude that Christ is, but we're trying to extract something from them.
And we can observe it. We know when we're doing it, because when we love people and serve people and they don't respond with gratitude or they're not grateful, they're not appreciative, they don't say thank you, or whatever we expect, and then our attitude is, I mean, not just to be sad for them, but to say, You know what?
That's it. I'm not going to serve them. I mean, they weren't grateful. I'm not going to care for them. They weren't appreciative of that. See, we don't have the same attitude that Christ did because our service isn't just loving someone and giving to them. We're trying to extract something from them, and that's not what it means.
So when we say Jesus is God, he's part of the triune God. Who then invites us into a loving relationship. So I love this passage because it gives us the most complete picture of who Jesus is. And the first thing is, is that Jesus is God. But the second thing that it tells us is that Jesus is human. Look at what it says in Philippians 2, 6 and 7. He did not think of equality with God as something to cling to.
Instead, he gave up his divine privileges. He took the humble position of a slave and was born as a human being when he appeared in human form. So Jesus is human, and he becomes human. He's both at once. It doesn't say having been God, he then becomes human. But it says being God, he also becomes human.
So he's both at the same time. Theologians call this the incarnation. And again, it's not something that I can totally explain how God can be both God and man, but I can tell you what it means to us because it has a profound implication. And it's this, that we have a God who understands us because he became like us. We are all wired to be connected, to live in relationship. We're designed that way, the Bible tells us, but it's not just because the Bible tells us.
Biologists say that as human beings, we're created to live connected to each other and in relationship. Social scientists do. Mental health experts do. Doctors do. And pastors all say we are designed to live in loving relationship.
We're designed to live connected, to be understood. And when you read the Bible in Genesis, you see that we are created and we live in loving relationship with God, literally walking with God in a garden. But God gives us this incredible choice with an incredible consequence. He says, You have freedom, and so you can choose to love me and to respond to me, or you can choose to go your own way. And sadly, we chose to have life on our own terms, and we destroyed everything.
We damaged our relationship with God and with each other. And the first thing that we do is there's this profound sense of shame. We're aware that we're not enough. We're unworthy. We're broken. And then we hide.
And because of that, that's what we do. And yet our primary need is to be connected. And the only way that we can be connected is when we're honest and vulnerable, and we're willing to connect with other people. And yet we're broken, and we're disconnected, and moving away from other people. But God loved us too much to leave us that way. So God comes to the earth 2,000 years ago in the person of Jesus, and look at what he does to restore relationship. He comes not as a king that is powerful, not as a God that is awesome and distant, but he comes as a baby in a manger.
He comes in weakness, and he's vulnerable, and he's small, and he's just like us. And he has to go through the same things that we do. He has to grow up. He falls. He skins his knees. He has to learn how to relate with other people. He's rejected. And then as an adult, he goes through all sorts of pain.
He was poor. He was part of a marginalized group. He was the wrong social group, and people looked down on his ethnicity. He understood sadness and loss. He lost an earthly father at an early age, and so he knows that. He had to grow up fast. He knows the pain of rejection, of friends. He knows what it's like to be belittled, to be mocked. He knows what it's like to suffer injustice and cruelty.
He even knows what it means to have an unanswered prayer. He knows what it means to face death and to die. And so this powerful thought that Jesus is human helps us understand that we have a God who understands us. This is the understanding love of God.
And when we forget this, we think that we're all alone and we live live at a distance and we think, if we start to pray, we go, But God, how could You understand? I mean, you don't know what it's like to feel brokenness, to feel weak, to be betrayed. And yet, when you look at Jesus, you realize that He understands everything that you have gone through. And because Jesus is human, we never have to wonder where God stands, because God stands with us.
He came to this earth to be with us. He knows, He's felt our pain. He knows He has compassion upon us. And the most amazing thing about the incarnation is that it is an eternal miracle. I mean, think of it. Jesus didn't just come to this earth for 33 years and then die, was resurrected, and go back to be what He was before.
The incarnation is an eternal miracle. Jesus forever becomes both at the same time. He is both God and He is both human at the same time. And so because He is God, He can take all of our sins. Because He is human, He can die ultimately for our sins. And so Jesus dies, and then God raises Him from the dead. And so today there is a man in heaven, the God-man, who intercedes for us and stands with us on our behalf.
And so we never have to worry for all of eternity. We have a God who understands and stands with us. So why would you stand away from God? Why would you be so afraid and distant and think that He doesn't care, that He doesn't understand? I mean, He did everything to come to you, to convince you that He understands the world that you live in and the life that you're living. So I love this passage.
It is the most complete picture of who Jesus is. It says clearly Jesus is God. It says that Jesus is human and that Jesus is a humble servant. Look at what it says in Philippians 2:8. He humbled Himself in obedience to God and died a criminal's death on a cross. This is the sacrificial love of God.
And so, you know, you just see when we forget this, look at how different we are from God, and yet we're supposed to be like who Jesus was. It says, though He was God, He did not think equality with God was something that He had to cling to. When we lose sight of that, how do we live? We go, though we are not God. See, what would we write about ourselves? Though we are not God, we think that being equal to God is something that we can grasp.
You say, no, I don't do that. We did that from the very beginning. That was the lie of Satan. If you do this, you will be like God. You go, well, how do I do that? Well, every time you and I know what God wants us to do, we read something in the Bible and we say, I don't care.
I'm going to do it my way. That's us putting ourselves in the place of God. Every time we try to control a situation, it's us trying to elevate ourselves to God. When we choose our own way, it's us trying to elevate our way to God. Instead, it says that Jesus gave up His divine privileges. He gave up the expression of His power, His glory, and His honor. And you think about us, we're constantly pursuing glory and honor.
We want people to honor us. And He says He took the humble position of a slave. He's dependent. We want to have slaves, and yet Jesus became a slave. And He says, being a human being, He humbled Himself. Self, he's vulnerable and weak. That's how you connect, and yet we try to be strong and powerful, which we can never can connect that way.
And then he humbled himself in obedience to God. Jesus's whole lifestyle was, Not my will, but your will. And our prayers are so often my own prayers are, God, not your will, my will, not your timing, my timing. God, not this is what I want. And then he died a criminal's death on a cross. And so Jesus, you look at the humiliation. He steps down. He was God.
He comes down. He becomes human. He becomes a servant. And then ultimately he dies on a cross. And there is no more humiliation than that. And it's not just a physical death, an emotional. I mean, this is a spiritual death. You have Jesus, who is absolutely holy and pure, and he lets sin infect him that is corrosive to his holiness and purity that destroys him.
And because he's God, he can take all of our sin, of all of humanity, and he can take it on him. And because he's both God and man, then he can die in our place for our sin. So he takes the penalty of our sin. He takes the consequences of our sin.
He destroys the power of sin so that he can give to us his righteousness and his purity. He brings us into his family to love us and to make us a part of that. And so that's what it means. And when we forget that, What happens is that somehow we think, you know, I need to earn it. And so we go out and we say, okay, I'll be really good, and we make promises to God, and we think that somehow if I work really hard and I try really hard, that God then will see my effort and He'll honor that and love me and go, Oh, you're great.
But ultimately, we just lie to ourselves. We're minimizing our sin. We're minimizing our brokenness. There's just no way that we can good our way to God. And so we just lie, and that's what the religious people did in Jesus' day. Or we go to the other extreme and we try, but we can't do it, and so we just despair, and so we quit.
But Jesus says, All you need to do is come to Me. You come to Me when you're overwhelmed with your sin and your brokenness. And He goes, I will give you forgiveness and love. I'll take your sin, and I'll give to you My righteousness. And so Jesus does that. And then look at what happens when Jesus humbles Himself. Look at what happens and how this passage ends.
Therefore God elevated Him to the place of highest honor and gave Him the name above all other names, that at the name of Jesus every knee should bow, in heaven and on earth and under the earth, and every tongue declare that Jesus Christ is Lord, to the glory of God the Father. Here what we see is Jesus didn't just stay on the cross and He didn't stay in the grave, but God raised Him from the dead and He put Him into the place of highest honor.
And so Jesus is God, the man who is in heaven, who's interceding for us, but also says that one day He's going to come back to our broken world and make everything right. And He's not going to come as a servant, but when He comes next time, He comes as a conquering King.
And what Paul writes in this passage is, he says, Every knee will bow and every tongue will confess that Jesus is Lord. Some will bow in gratitude, thanking Jesus. Jesus for his love and his forgiveness, that he's invited us into his family and made us his. And others will bow in horror and fear, feeling the full weight of their sin, realizing that it is just too late. And that's why Jesus says over and again, You do not want to go into eternity holding on to your sin.
But when we started this passage, remember the very first line? What the reason Paul writes it all. Look at what he says in Philippians 2:5. You must have the same attitude that Christ Jesus had. We have to have the same lifestyle, the same way of thinking, that we have to be humble like Jesus was.
And this passage tells us what humility is. The definition of humility is that we consider others more important than ourselves. Now, that doesn't mean that we view ourselves as worthless or useless. It just means—I love what John Stott says. He says this. He says, It's not to think less of ourselves; it's to think of ourselves less.
So God doesn't dislike when his children are honored, and he doesn't want us to live as a victim. That's not what humility means. And it doesn't mean that we don't think of ourselves. It just means that we think of ourselves less. And so we see that we are called to live a life of humility, and it makes sense to us, because what it says is the only way that people will be loved and cared for is if someone is willing to step down and to serve and to be humble.
The only way that children are raised in confidence and that we have healthy families is if parents sacrifice and serve. The only way that marriages thrive and spouses are loved is if someone surrenders, or if they put another ahead of themselves, or they keep no record of wrongs.
The only way friends are encouraged is if somebody is willing to be humble and step aside and say, Go ahead. The only way a church is really a redemptive community and is a beautiful picture of Jesus in the world today is when we, as his followers, step down and surrender and humble ourselves and live as servants. There is no way for you and I to increase and live a life of selfishness and to see people's lives changed and to see people come to Jesus.
And Jesus did not step down and humble himself and sacrifice so that his followers can step on, step over, and step up. It's not the way we were called to live. Jesus, when he was here, he said, I did not come to be served. I came to serve and to give my life.
And then Jesus says, So now I send you out, and I want you to love in the same way that I've loved. I want you to be a servant. And so he sends us in the world to serve. And the most amazing thing, as we read through the New Testament, it says that when we serve each other, that God supercharges our efforts and it makes a difference in people's lives. When we serve others, it literally says that it mends and heals people, and that we build up the body of Christ, and so that there is unity until we all become mature and we're growing and we become more like Jesus.
And so when you serve, you have this promise from God that it's going to make an eternal difference in people's lives, that he's going to make sure. So it's not just your efforts. God is going to bless your efforts, supercharge your efforts, so that you make a powerful difference. And so we get involved in that. This is why Jesus said in Matthew 23:11, The greatest among you...
Must be a servant. And then in Luke 22, he says, But among you, it will be different. Those who are the greatest among you should take the lowest rank, and the leader should be a servant. What Jesus, you know, in the world—what's the world's definition of greatness? It is to be powerful and to have money and strength and status and to just press your influence into the world.
But Jesus says, Not so with you. He says, With you, the greatest is a servant, and we change the world when we serve. And the best part of it is, Jesus says, everyone can be great because everyone can serve. And so when we get involved and we serve together, the church together as the body of Christ, we become like Jesus to the world, and people see it and they become awestruck.
The Bible describes the church and the way it's supposed to be in the book of Acts and the very first church. And I love the picture that it paints in Acts chapter 2 because it says when the church got together and it was doing everything that it should do, there was a sense of awe. People just would look at it and go, That is so powerful.
That is miraculous. And they just lived in awe. And so what's a word that we use for awe? We would say, Wow. You know, when you see the church being what it's supposed to be, and people serving and loving, they go, Wow. And so in Acts it says the church would get together and they would devote themselves to God's word.
That's what we're doing right now. We're studying God's word and surrendering our life to it. And when people see God's people surrendering themselves to God's word, they'd look at that and they'd go, Wow. And then when people would get together as God's family and they'd worship. And praise God in large groups, and they'd see people lifting their hands and praising and singing, they would go, Wow, look at that.
And then they would gather in small groups, in homes, and they'd pray for each other, and they'd be vulnerable and honest, and they'd share their lives, and they'd support each other, and they saw that, and they saw the miracles as they prayed. People would go, Wow, look at that, because of the fellowship.
And when people, the church, got together and they would serve each other in love and trust that God supercharged that, and the supernatural happened, and lives were being changed, and lives were being mended and built up, and people were becoming more like Jesus, people went, Wow, look at that. And as a result of that, there was the miraculous, and every day more and more people came to know Jesus as their Savior, and people go, Wow.
And that's what we're called to do. We're to have the same attitude that Jesus had. We are called to show up as servants, and that's really the opportunity that you have. And so what we want to do is give you the opportunity to serve.
And so for those of you that are online, you can serve in your family and you can serve in your business, but you can serve in your church. We have some incredible opportunities. On the prayer team, you can see service as host, as ESL facilitators. All you have to do is text SERVE to the number that you see on the screen, and we will help you serve together, because when we serve together, we change the world, and the world will go, Wow. All right?
Pray with me. Father, we are so grateful that you love us and that you've invited us into this loving family. You saved us and rescued us. And we honor that you are God, but you are human, and that you wonderfully on the cross died for our sins so that we could be forgiven. We are so grateful. We are so grateful. We pray in Jesus' name. Amen.